Guide to the Howard Zinn Papers TAM.542
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Howard Zinn Papers
Bulk, 1944-2010
1901-2010
TAM.542
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
85.25 linear feet in 83 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 oversize flat box, 1 oversize poster box and 1 flat file drawer.
Howard Zinn (1922-2010) was an award-winning historian, activist, playwright, teacher, public speaker and author of articles, essays and books including his best-selling A People’s History of the United States. Praised for his moral courage and passion for social justice, Zinn influenced thousands of students during a teaching career of more than thirty years. Reaching the wider public through his books, plays, articles, lectures and in theatrical and television presentations of his Voices of A People’s History and The People Speak, Zinn celebrated the lives of ordinary individuals engaged in the struggle for peace and justice, highlighting their often overlooked victories, and encouraging his audiences to engage as well. This collection provides a broad view of Howard Zinn’s many activities and interests. Among his personal papers are school and military records, datebooks, biographical articles and interviews. Correspondence with a wide variety of individuals forms a large part of the collection. There are also published and unpublished writings; drafts, fragments and corrected typescripts; datebooks and notebooks; research materials and lecture notes; posters, photographs and transparencies; annotated books, publications of many kinds, and audio and video materials documenting lectures, interviews, discussions, readings and other public events in which Zinn took part.
Zinn, Howard, 1922-2010
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of much of the original media, items in Series X: Audio Visual Material must have digital surrogates made before they can be used by researchers. Requests should be sent to tamiment.wagner@library.nyu.edu.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Howard Zinn (1922-2010) was an award-winning historian, activist, playwright, teacher, public speaker and author of articles, essays and books including the best-selling A People’s History of the United States. Praised for his moral courage and passion for social justice, Zinn influenced thousands of students during a teaching career of more than thirty years. Reaching the wider public through his books, plays, articles, lectures and in theatrical and television presentations of his Voices of A People’s History and The People Speak, Zinn celebrated the lives of ordinary individuals engaged in the struggle for peace and justice, highlighting their often overlooked victories, and encouraging his audiences to engage as well.
Born on August 24, 1922, Howard Zinn was one of four sons of working-class Jewish immigrants Edward and Jennie (Rabinowitz) Zinn. Growing up in Brooklyn, he held after school and summer jobs from the age of fourteen, graduated from Thomas Jefferson High School, and worked as an apprentice ship fitter at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. In early 1943, he joined the Army Air Corps, attaining the rank of Second Lieutenant. He trained as a bombardier and flew both combat and humanitarian missions in Europe. In 1944 he married Roslyn Shechter and, after the war, they lived in public housing and began raising a family while he attended New York University on the GI Bill and worked at a variety of menial jobs. Earning an undergraduate degree from NYU in 1951, Zinn continued his education at Columbia University, completing his MA in 1952 and PhD in 1958. In 1960-1961, he was a post-doctoral fellow in East Asian Studies at Harvard University.
After part-time lecturing in history and political science (1953-1956) at Upsala College in New Jersey, Zinn accepted a position at Spelman College in Atlanta as Chairman of the Department of History and Social Sciences (1956). During his seven years at Spelman, an all-black women’s college, he became deeply involved in the civil rights movement – mentoring student activists, participating in sit-ins and other actions, advising the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and producing articles for publications such as The Nation and Harper’s. His activism made him unpopular with the school’s administration and, in 1963, he was dismissed. Forty-one years later, in 2005, Zinn was invited to give Spelman’s commencement address and the school awarded him an honorary Doctor of Humane Letters.
In 1964 Zinn published two books focusing on the civil rights movement – SNCC: The New Abolitionists and The Southern Mystique—and also accepted a teaching position at Boston University.
His 24 years at BU were marked by overbooked classes and clashes with the administration, as well as teach-ins, strikes, debates, rallies and the writing of many articles, essays and books including two of particular note – Vietnam: The Logic of Withdrawal (1967), one of the first to strongly condemn US actions in Vietnam, and A People’s History of the Unites States (1980), his most popular work. Noam Chomsky describes this as “his enduring masterpiece”, a book that communicates Zinn’s “fundamental message about the crucial role of the people who remain unknown in carrying forward the endless struggle for peace and justice…”
Howard Zinn retired from Boston University in 1988. His relatively early retirement allowed him to concentrate on speaking and writing and to continue participating in demonstrations, protests, strikes and acts of civil disobedience which, on some occasions, resulted in his arrest. He spoke out against capital punishment and for improved prison conditions, expressed strong concerns about the environment and nuclear issues, consistently criticized US foreign policy in Central America and elsewhere, and was strongly opposed to the invasion and occupation of Iraq.
In 2002, Harper Collins celebrated the sale of one million copies of A People’s History of the United States with a New York City performance of readings based on the book. This was followed in 2004 by publication of Voices of a People’s History of the United States in which Zinn and Anthony Arnove collected speeches, articles, essays, poetry and song lyrics by the individuals described in A People’s History. Public performances of selections from Voices culminated in the production of a feature film, The People Speak, in 2009. The film features Zinn, along with well-known entertainers such as Matt Damon, Morgan Freeman, Bob Dylan, Bruce Springsteen, Viggo Mortensen, Marisa Tomei, Josh Brolin and Danny Glover. These performances, as well as references to Zinn in popular culture, including a mention in the 1997 film Good Will Hunting, significantly increased the number of his readers and viewers. In 2008, the nonprofit Zinn Education Project was established to provide teaching materials based on Zinn’s work to educators at the secondary school level insuring that his views on history, politics and social justice would continue to be introduced to young audiences.
Howard Zinn died on January 27, 2010. He and his wife Roslyn, who died in 2008, had two children, Myla Kabat-Zinn and Jeff Zinn, and five grandchildren. Zinn’s life and work are described in his 1995 autobiography You Can’t be Neutral on a Moving Train which was released in 2004 as a documentary film of the same name.
Scope and Content Note
This collection provides a broad view of Howard Zinn’s many activities and interests. Among his personal papers are school and military records, datebooks, biographical articles and interviews. Correspondence with a wide variety of individuals forms a large part of the collection. There are also published and unpublished writings; drafts, fragments and corrected typescripts; datebooks and notebooks; research materials and lecture notes; posters, photographs and transparencies; annotated books, publications of many kinds, and audio and video materials documenting lectures, interviews, discussions, readings and other public events in which Zinn took part.
Correspondence is found in almost every series. The correspondence included in "Series II: Correspondence" is the most varied, containing letters, emails, postcards and related materials that Zinn had consolidated and arranged by year. Letters in "Series I: Personal and Biographical Material" involve family and close friends, and are personal in nature, while within "Series III: Writings", much of the correspondence reflects communication with publishers, editors, actors and others involved in his various projects. Zinn associated the remaining correspondence with specific topics, individuals, events or issues being addressed and that arrangement has been maintained.
Howard Zinn’s extensive travels outside the United States are reflected in many parts of the collection. In addition to material in “Series VII: Vietnam War” describing his visits to Vietnam, Paris and Japan, there are a number of folders in “Series VIII: Subject Files” containing publications, clippings and notes from his 1982 visit to South Africa as well as a copy of the speech he gave in Cape Town in “Series III: Writings.” He made a number of trips to Paris (1974, 1978, 1984) where he was a visiting professor at the University of Paris (Vincennes and Institut Charles Civiq) and to Italy as a Fulbright Distinguished Professor at the University of Bologna (1995). Personal correspondence and memorabilia from these and other European travels, as well as from his South African visit and several trips to Cuba, may be found in “Series I: Personal and Biographical Material.”
There are many articles and newspaper clippings throughout the collection. It should be noted that he often clipped only the portions of articles that interested him, sometimes saving an initial section and not the continuation. The name of the publication and date of the article were not always saved.
Related Archival Material
Howard Zinn Papers, 1956-1970
The Wisconsin Historical Society holds a small manuscript collection acquired from Howard Zinn (1966, 1980) focusing primarily on Zinn's research on the civil rights movement and his personal involvement with the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) during the 1960s. The Wisconsin Historical Society finding aid may be accessed at http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/wiarchives.uw-whs-mss00588.
Separated Materials
A number of books from Howard Zinn's personal library were acquired with his papers and many of them were transferred to the Tamiment Library.(The more heavily annotated books were retained with the papers - see Series IX.)
Arrangement
The Howard Zinn Papers are arranged into ten series, three of which are further arranged into subseries. Folders within each series and subseries are arranged alphabetically with several exceptions: appearances/speaking engagements are in chronological order as are audio-visual materials within each format and correspondence within specific sections.
The series arrangement of the collection is as follows:
Series I: Personal and Biographical Material, 1944-2010
Series II: Correspondence, 1962-2010
Series III: Writings, 1901-2009
Series IV: Appearances / Speaking Engagements. 1964-2008
Series V: Boston University, 1960-2003
Subseries VA: Teaching and Student Material
Subseries VB: Boston University Controversy
Series VI: Race and Civil Rights, 1932-2008
Series VII: Vietnam War, 1944-2001
Subseries VIIA: Vietnam War Material
Subseries VIIB: The Pentagon Papers
Series VIII: Subject Files, 1933-2010
Series IX: Books with Zinn Annotations, 1929-1997
Series X: Audio-Visual Material, 1957-2009
Subseries XA: Audio Cassettes
Subseries XB: Audio Compact Disks
Subseries XC: Audio Reel-to-Reel
Subseries XD: Video DVDs
Subseries XE: Video VHS
Subseries XF: Video, Other Formats
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Howard Zinn Papers were acquired from his children, Myla Kabat-Zinn and Jeff Zinn, in 2010 and 2011.
Bibliography
Robert Cohen, “When Assessing Zinn, Listen to the Voices of Teachers and Students,” in History News Network (George Mason University, January 17, 2013) is based on correspondence housed in the Howard Zinn Papers. (@http://hnn.us/articles/when-assessing-zinn-listen-voices-teachers-and-students)
Abu-Jamal, Mumia; Ahmad, Eqbal; American Association of University Professors.; American Civil Liberties Union.; Berrigan, Daniel; Berrigan, Philip; Boudin, Kathy; Chomsky, Noam.; Ellsberg, Daniel.; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Lynd, Staughton.; Marx, Karl, 1818-1883; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Piven, Frances Fox; Silber, John, 1926-; United States. Central Intelligence Agency.; Vonnegut, Kurt; Walker, Alice, 1944-; Zinn, Howard, 1922-2010; Academic freedom |z United States.; Afghan War, 2001-; Anti-war demonstrations.; Antinuclear movement |z United States.; Appointment books.; Articles.; Audiovisual materials.; Boston (Mass.); China.; Civil disobedience |z United States.; Civil rights.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Draft resisters.; Economics.; Ephemera.; Essays.; Federal Bureau of Investigation surveillance files.; Historians |z United States.; Interviews.; Iraq War, 2003-2011.; Legal documents.; Middle East.; Newspapers.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Pamphlets.; Peace movements.; Photographs.; Plays (document genres).; Posters.; Prisoners |v Correspondence.; Prisons |z United States.; Race relations in the United States.; Research notes.; Reviews (document genre); Scripts (documents).; Speeches.; Terrorism.; Transparencies.; Trials (Political crimes and offenses) |z United States.; United States |x History.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |x Protest movements |z United States.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; War resistance movements |z United States.
- Series I: Personal and Biographical Material, 1944-2010
  Scope and Content Note
  The initial series in this collection contains a variety of personal materials as well as biographical articles and interviews. Among its highlights are school and military records, photographs, datebooks (1967-2008) and trip memorabilia.
  Personal correspondence includes letters from family members and friends; Daniel and Philip Berrigan, Kurt Vonnegut and Alice Walker are among the more well-known. In addition, there is correspondence and related material that describes Zinn's dismissal from Spelman College as well as letters of support and good wishes on his retirement from Boston University. One folder within this series contains recipes that had been clipped by Zinn and were found here and there within the collection.
  Several folders contain portions of the Federal Bureau of Investigation file maintained on Howard Zinn beginning in 1949 (File # 100-30217). In July 2010 the FBI released the file; it may be accessed in two sections at http://www.archive.org/details/Howard.Zinn_FBI.file_pt.1 and http://www.archive.org/details/Howard_Zinns_FBI_file_pdf_2_and_3.
  - Address Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arrests and Testimony, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Awards and Recognition: Eugene V. Debs Award, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Awards and Recognition: Lannan Literary Awards, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards and Recognition: Thomas Merton Award, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Awards and Recognition: Upton Sinclair Award, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Awards and Recognition: Various, 1987-2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biographical Articles (Zinn, by others), 1968-2007, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Biographical Data, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Personal (includes letters from Robert J. Lifton and from Noam Chomsky), 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Personal, 1974-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: Personal (includes letter from William Sloane Coffin), 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Personal (includes e-mail from Daniel Ellsberg), 2000-2009 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: Personal (includes letters from Staughton Lynd), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Berrigan, Dan and Phil Berrigan (also Elizabeth McAlister), 1968-2003, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Carlsson-Paige, Nancy (mother of Matt Damon), 1998, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Cook, Samuel DuBois, 1965-1966, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Oladele, Jeanne Jackson (many observations of Nigerian coup and civil war; several essays included), 1965-1968, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Oladele, Jeanne Jackson (Nigerian newspaper clippings sent to Zinn with correspondence), 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, Bologna (Italy), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, Japan, [Jun 1966] (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, Paris (includes letter from Jane Fonda), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, Paris, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Trips, South Africa, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Vonnegut, Kurt, 1998-2006 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: Personal - Walker, Alice (includes related material, mostly arranged by Zinn), 1962-1987, 1994, 1996, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Datebooks, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Datebooks, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Datebooks, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Datebooks, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Datebooks, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Datebooks, 1986-1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Datebooks, 1990-1993 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Datebooks, 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Datebooks, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Datebooks, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Datebooks, 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Datebooks, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Datebooks, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Datebooks, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Datebooks: Roslyn Zinn, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - "Diary of a Teacher", 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Diplomas: Columbia University (MA and PhD), 1952, 1958 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) File, 1949-1953, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) File, 1955-1971, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) File, 1965-1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) File, 1965-1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Fulbright Scholar: University of Bologna, Italy (includes letter from John Kerry), 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Interviews, 1968, 1973, 1988, 1992-2008, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Journal Pages, [1975], undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Memorial Service: "A Celebration of the Life of Howard Zinn" - Poster (oversize), 2010; Not currently available - awaiting preservation housing (Flat-file Top of FFC: 1-4)
  - Memorial Service: "A Celebration of the Life of Howard Zinn" - Posters and Gary Huck Caricature, 2010 (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - Memorial Service: "A Celebration of Howard Zinn" - Program, Mar 27, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Military: American Veterans Committee - Suspension, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Military: Army Air Force (AAF), 1944-1946 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Military: Army Discharge Papers, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Military: Royan - Bombing, Research Materials (correspondence, notes and drafts), 1967, 1969, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Military: World War II Photos and Mementos (includes flight log, aerial map, photos of planes and bombing), 1944-1945, 1974, 1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Military: World War II Photos and Mementos - May 1945 Issues (2) of Yank, The Army Weekly (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Military: World War II Reunion - Certificate of Appreciation, 2004 (Box 85, Folder 3)
  - Notes (personal), 1965, 1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Notes: Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Obituary (Japanese), 2010 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Personal Ephemera, 1978, 1994, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, 2002-2004, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Photos" (includes postcards and related items), 1973-1986, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Recipes, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Retirement from Boston University: Clippings, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Retirement from Boston University: Correspondence from Students and Others, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - School Records (includes transcripts, certificates, awards), 1946-1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Shechter, Alice: Letter and Creative Writing Exercise (Shechter is Roslyn Zinn's niece), 2004, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Spelman College, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Spelman College: Daily Journal, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Spelman College: Dismissal, 1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Spelman College: Dismissal - Articles, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Spelman College: Dismissal - Correspondence, Mar 1963 - Jul 1963 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Spelman College: Dismissal - Correspondence, Aug 1963 - 1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Spelman College: Dismissal - Correspondence and Associated Material ("Last Spelman File"), 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Spelman College: Dismissal - "An Expression of Student Concern", [1963] (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Spelman College: Dismissal - Zinn Statements and Related Materials, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Spelman College: Honors Thesis - "Birth of Consciousness: Activism at Spelman College, 1953-1965" by Molly Blank, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Spelman College: Yearbook "Reflections 1960" (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Spelman College: Zinn Commencement Speech, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Spelman College: Zinn Honorary Degree, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Trips: Cuba 1992, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Trips: Cuba 2004, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Trips: Cuba 2004 - Honorary Degree, University of Havana (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Trips: Cuba 2005 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Trips: Europe (correspondence, mementos; Hungary, Italy, London...), 1987 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Trips: Greece, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Trips: Italy (correspondence, clippings and talk in Rome), 2005 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Trips: Paris 1974, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Trips: Paris 1974 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Trips: Paris 1978, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Trips: Paris 1984, 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Trips: South Africa (correspondence, mementos), 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Trips: Spain (correspondence, mementos), 1990 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Various Articles that Mention Zinn, 1977-2007, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Vonnegut, Kurt: Remembrance by Zinn, 2007-2008 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "War in a Glass Case": School Essay [Columbia University], 1950 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Watercolor Sketch of Howard Zinn, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1962-2010
  Spanning almost fifty years, Series II contains a wide variety of correspondence from strangers, acquaintances, colleagues and publishers. Much of the material could be classified as fan mail although there are critical letters as well. Many of the correspondents are involved in progressive causes championed by Zinn and the letters often reflect the personal experiences of those for whom Zinn’s writings resonate. There are also requests for job or school references as well as letters asking for Zinn’s participation in a variety of events and projects. Some of the correspondence is neither to nor from Zinn, but appears to have been shared with him by others.
  Zinn’s annotations appear on some of the material and there are retained copies of a few of his responses. In a good number of instances, related items are included with the incoming letters (e.g., articles, reviews, clippings). Some well-known persons may be found within this series. Examples include Bill Moyers, Pete Seeger, Herbert Aptheker, Eqbal Ahmad and Noam Chomsky.